Guide to the Walter Freeman and James Watts collection, 1918-1988 MS0803.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- James Watts Papers, 1926-1982; MS0803 Series 2; 12.5 Linear feet (Box 42, Box 33, Box 34, Box 31, Box 32, Box 29, Box 30, Box 27, Box 28, Box 35, Box 43, Box 40, Box 41, Box 38, Box 39, Box 36, Box 37, Box 24, Box 23, Box 26, Box 25)
  - Publications, 1926-1982; MS0803 Subseries 2.4
    - Neurology and Neurological Surgery: Its Story at George Washington University, 1965 (Box 34, Folder 45)
    - The Surgical Treatment of Craniosynostosis, 1967 (Box 34, Folder 46)
  - Conference Papers and Lectures, 1926-1982; MS0803 Subseries 2.5
    - 9th Latin American Congress of Neurology, Mexico City, 10/04/1961-10/10/1961 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - 10th Annual National Assembly of Surgeons, Hospital Juarez, Mexico City, 11/09/1952-11/15/1952 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - American Neurological Association, 1963 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Angiography in Neurosurgery, with Robert H. Groh, Southeastern Surgical Congress, Hollywood, FL [1/2], 04/1951 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Angiography in Neurosurgery, extra photos [2/2], 04/1951 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Clinical Observations on the Relation of the Temporal Lobe to Vestibular Disorders, International Symposium on Temporal Lobes, Mexico City, 11/15/1964-11/20/1964 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - The Clinical Value of Lobotomy, Guild of Catholic Psychiatrists, Washington, DC, 02/10/1958-02/11/1958 (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Clinicopathological Conference, Atlantic City Hospital, Atlantic City, NJ, 08/05/1957-08/09/1957 (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Discussion by James Watts of the Value of the Grantham Lobotomy by Frank J. Ayd, Southern Medical Association, Washington, DC, 11/12/1956-11/15/1956 (Box 35, Folder 9)
    - Fifth Annual Meeting, American College of Surgeons, San Juan, Puerto Rico, 02/24/1955-02/26/1955 (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - First International Congress of Neurological Sciences, Brussels, 07/21/1957-07/28/1957 (Box 35, Folder 11)
    - Frontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Unbearable Pain, Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Disease, New York, 12/12/1947-12/13/1947 (Box 35, Folder 12)
    - Gill Memorial Eye, Ear, and Throat Hospital, Roanoke, VA, 1957-1958 (Box 35, Folder 13)
    - Harvey Cushing Society, Twenty-Fourth Annual Meeting, Honolulu, Hawaii, 04/16/1956-04/18/1956 (Box 35, Folder 14)
    - Harvey Cushing Society, New Orleans, LA, 04/30/1959-05/02/1959 (Box 35, Folder 15)
    - Harvey Cushing Society, Twenty-Ninth Annual Meeting, Mexico City, 04/16/1961-04/19/1961 (Box 35, Folder 16)
    - Influence of Lobotomy on Drug Addiction due to Pain, Southern Neurological Society, Nashville, TN, 02/04/1060-02/06/1960 (Box 35, Folder 17)
    - The Influence of Malpractice Suits on Surgery, Southeastern Surgical Congress, Baltimore, MD [1/2], 03/10/1958-03/13/1958 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Conferences papers, Lectures: The Influence of Malpractice Suits on Surgery, Southeastern Surgical Congress, Baltimore, MD [2/2], 03/10/1958-03/13/1958 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Injuries to Spinal Cord Upper Lumbar Spine, International College of Surgeons, 1957 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Intelligence Following Prefrontal Lobotomy in Obsessive Tension States (with Freeman), Philadelphia Neurological Society, 03/1944 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Intelligence Following Prefrontal Lobotomy in Obsessive Tension States, Harvey Cushing Society, New York, 05/17/1944-05/18/1944 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - International College of Surgeons conferences, 1946-1947 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - International College of Surgeons, Sao Paulo, Brazil, 04/1954 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - International College of Surgeons, Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic, 10/1956 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - International College of Surgeons, White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia, 02/10/1957-02/13/1957 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - International Conference on Psychosurgery, Lisbon, 08/03/1948-08/07/1948 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Interstate Medical Association of North America, Cleveland, Ohio, 11/09/1948-11/12/1948 (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - Involutional Melancholia, West Virginia Academy of General Practice, Charleston, West Virginia, 05/16/1953-05/17/1953 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Lecture to nurses on history of neurosurgical technics, George Washington University, 02/06/1980 (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - Lecture on Psychosurgery, University of Virginia, 04/16/1952 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Lectures on psychosurgery and pain, Veterans Hospital, Albuquerque, NM, 02/14/1949-02/15/1949 (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - Medical Society of the State of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, 10/12/1958-10/17/1958 (Box 36, Folder 16)
    - Meig's Society, Philadelphia, 1948 (Box 36, Folder 17)
    - National Cancer Conference, Memphis, Tennessee, 02/25/1949-02/27/1949 (Box 36, Folder 18)
    - Neurological Treatment of Tic Douloureux and Intractable Pain, Medical Society of the District of Columbia, 02/15/1955-02/17/1955 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Orientation Program for First Year Medical Students, 09/16/1958-09/19/1958 (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - Post Graduate Symposium on Surgery, University of Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic, 10/1956 (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: The Critical Plane of Section, Harvey Cushing Society, Kansas City, MO, 05/02/1940-05/04/1940 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - Pre Frontal Lobotomy: Factors Influencing the Prognosis, Tri-State Medical Association, Richmond, VA, 02/25/1946-02/26/1946 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy: Six Years Experience, with Walter Freeman, Southern Medical Association, 11/10/1942-11/12/1942 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Certain Mental Disorders, GW Faculty luncheon, 10/31/1936 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Prefrontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Unbearable Pain, Tri-State Medical Association, Greensboro, North Carolina, 03/03/1947-03/04/1947 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    - Proceedings of the First Postgraduate Course in Psychosurgery, GW School of Medicine, 01/24/1949-01/28/1949 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    - Program from Third International Congress of Neurological Surgery, Copenhagen, 08/22/1965-08/27/1965 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    - Psychosurgery, Oklahoma State Medical Association, Tulsa. Oklahoma, 05/15/1947-05/16/1947 (Box 37, Folder 11)
    - Psychosurgery, Veterans Administration Hospital, Fort Logan, Colorado, 02/16/1949 (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Psychosurgery: A 20 Year Follow-up of the Freeman-Watts Series, Tenth Anniversary Meeting of the Nacional Instituto Neurologia, Mexico City [1/2], 11/03/1974-11/08/1974 (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Psychosurgery: A 20 Year Follow-up of the Freeman-Watts Series, Tenth Anniversary Meeting of the Nacional Instituto Neurologia, Mexico City [2/2], 11/03/1974-11/08/1974 (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - Psychosurgery: Accomplishments, Limitations, and Risks in the Management of Intractable Pain, American Medical Association, Atlantic City, NJ, 06/11/1951-06/15/1951 (Box 37, Folder 15)
    - Psychosurgery: Accomplishments, Limitations, and Risks in the Management of Intractable Pain, First Mexican Conference of Neurological Surgery, 11/1952 (Box 37, Folder 16)
    - Psychosurgery: Effect on Certain Mental Symptoms of Surgical Interruption of Pathways in the Frontal Lobe (with Walter Freeman), AMA section on Nervous and Mental Diseases, Atlantic City, NJ, 06/09/1937 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - Psychosurgery for the Relief of Unbearable Pain, with Walter Freeman, International College of Surgeons, Washington, DC, 12/07/1945 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - Psychosurgery program for The National Presbyterian Center, 07/06/1973 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Recent Observations on the diagnosis and Pathologic Anatomy of Posterior Fossa Meningiomas, Symposium to honor Dr. A. Earl Walker, Johns Hopkins, 04/07/1967-04/08/1967 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Recent Progress in Neurosurgery, Medical Arts Society of the District of Columbia, 03/14/1940 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Rehabilitation Following Injury to the Spinal Cord, International College of Surgeons, Mexico City, 02/23/1957-03/01/1957 (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Rehabilitation of Mental Patients by Prefrontal Lobotomy, St. Elizabeth's Hospital, Richmond, VA, 01/27/1941 (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - The Relation of the Cerebral Cortex to Urinary Incontinence, American Psychiatric Association, 05/13/1935 (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - Saint Albans Sanatorium, Radford, Virginia, 04/18/1947 (Box 38, Folder 9)
    - Second National Conference on World Health, World Health Organization, Washington, DC, 05/07/2959-05/09/1959 (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - Southern Medical Association, St. Louis, MO, 10/31/1060-11/03/1960 (Box 38, Folder 11)
    - Southeastern Surgical Congress, Baltimore, Maryland, 03/10/1958-03/13/1958 (Box 38, Folder 12)
    - Stroke workshop, Washington Hospital Center, 04/13/1970 (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - Surgery of the Intervertebral Disc, International College of Surgeons, 09/16/1953 (Box 38, Folder 14)
    - Surgery for Pain Relief, GW Medical School, 03/22/1955 (Box 38, Folder 15)
    - Symposium on Neurology, Freiberg, Germany, 07/05/1054-07/10/1954 (Box 38, Folder 16)
    - Teaching of Neurosurgery in the United States of America, 1st Mexican Congress of Neurological Surgery, 09/29/1969-10/03/1969 (Box 38, Folder 17)
    - Conferences papers, Lectures: Teaching of Neurosurgery in the United States with comments on Programs in Other Countries, Neurosurgical Associates of Pittsburgh, 04/1970 (Box 38, Folder 18)
    - Thorotrast in Neurological Diagnosis, Baltimore Neurological Society, 01/1941 (Box 38, Folder 19)
    - Tri State Medical Association, Old Point Comfort, Virginia, 02/21/1955-02/22/1955 (Box 38, Folder 20)
    - The Value of Combining Sedation of the Central and Autonomic Nervous Systems in the Treatment of Epilepsy, District of Columbia Medical Society, 04/15/1937 (Box 38, Folder 21)
    - Veteran's Administration Center, San Juan, Puerto Rico, 1948-1955 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - Veteran's Administration Center, San Juan, Puerto Rico, 1950 (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - VA Hospital, Salt Lake City, UT, 02/1949-07/1949 (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - Visual Fields, Pupils, and other Ocular Signs Associated with Tumors of the Lateral Geniculate Body and Superior Colliculus, Washington, DC Ophthalmological Society, 03/01/1937 (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Working Ability after Lobotomy, Southern Medical Association, 11/05/1951-11/08/1951 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Research, 1926-1982; MS0803 Subseries 2.6
    - Anterior Scalen Syndrome, 1945 ca. (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - Bilateral Prefrontal Area Amputation in Monkey, 1937 (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - Frontal Lobe Tumors notes, 1935 ca. (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - Frontal Lobe Tumors (paper "A Systematic Survey of 105 Verified Tumors involving the Frontal Lobe Alone," by Charles Frazier), 1935 (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - Information Blank, Cerebral Palsy Consultation Clinic, 1940 ca. (Box 39, Folder 10)
    - Lobotomy Operative Results [Schraeder's lobotomies], undated (Box 39, Folder 11)
    - Low Back Pain Associated with Sciatic Pain, 100 Consecutive Cases, 1955 ca. (Box 39, Folder 12)
    - Notebook on research surgery, 1933-1934 (Box 39, Folder 14)
    - Notebook on research surgery on cats, 1934 (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - Psychosurgery Neurological Aspects, 1952 ca. (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - Report of Dr. Watts' Transorbital Lobotomy cases, undated (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Some Aspects of Treatment of Epilepsy with Drugs, 1935 (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - Statistics on lobotomies, 1957 ca. (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - Study of the Use of Psychosurgery in the United States by Miriam Kelly, 1974 ca. (Box 40, Folder 6)
    - Thalamus, 1950 ca. (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - The Treatment of Epilepsy: Non-Surgical, 1936 ca. (Box 40, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, Postcard, and Slides, 1926-1982; MS0803 Subseries 2.7
    - 50th year reunion of Watts' class at VMI, 05/1974 (Box 40, Folder 9)
    - Building used for meetings on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 10)
    - Cushing Society, 70th birthday of Harvey Cushing, 1939 (Box 40, Folder 11)
    - Five men talking at meeting on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 12)
    - Former residents of James Watts' who appear in the oil portrait of Watts by Robert Fantuzzi, 1965 ca. (Box 40, Folder 13)
    - Four men talking on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 14)
    - Group of men talking on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 15)
    - James and Julia Watts with family members, 1968-1969 (Box 40, Folder 16)
    - James Watts (in foreground) with other men on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 17)
    - James Watts (left) with man on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 18)
    - Photographs: James Watts (left) with two men on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 19)
    - James Watts (middle) in surgical gown conferring with other doctors, 1955 ca. (Box 40, Folder 20)
    - James Watts (middle) with two men on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 21)
    - James Watts and family members, 1920ca.-1950-- --ca. (Box 40, Folder 22)
    - James Watts at dinner with colleagues (negatives included), 03/1964 (Box 40, Folder 23)
    - James Watts at podium of dinner party, 1950 ca. (Box 40, Folder 24)
    - James Watts looking at materials related to lobotomy on exhibit at Himmelfarb Library, 1982 (Box 40, Folder 25)
    - James Watts sitting at his office desk, 1982 (Box 40, Folder 26)
    - James Watts standing before oil portrait by Robert Fantuzzi, in Himmelfarb Library, 1982 (Box 40, Folder 27)
    - James Watts with another man at a conference, 1960 ca. (Box 40, Folder 28)
    - Large group of men with Watts in front row (facing forward) on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 29)
    - Large group of men with Watts in front row (facing forward) on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 30)
    - Large group of men with Watts in front row (facing right) on Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 31)
    - Oil portrait of James Watts by Robert Fantuzzi in Himmelfarb Library (with text describing it), 1970 ca. (Box 40, Folder 32)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 40, Folder 33)
    - Unitarian Services, Inc. trip to Germany, 1954 (Box 40, Folder 34)
    - Watts on boat with others, 1955 ca. (Box 40, Folder 35)
    - Three men listening to a lecture, 1975 ca. (Box 40, Folder 36)
    - Negatives: Unidentified scenes, 1950 ca. (Box 40, Folder 37)
    - Negatives: Winston Watts, 08/1941 (Box 40, Folder 38)
    - Slides: James Watts and other men, 03/1964 (Box 40, Folder 39)
    - Postcards: Pictures of Egaz Moniz' home from Dr. Alcinda de Aguiar, 1950 ca. (Box 40, Folder 40)
    - Lantern slide: Cartoon from New York Times, "French Premier and E.D.C. As Mr. Low Sees the Situation,", 08/22/1954 (Box 40, Folder 41)
  - Videotape and Film, 1926-1982; MS0803 Subseries 2.8
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W1, undated (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W2, undated (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W3, undated (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W4, undated (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W5, undated (Box 41, Folder 5)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W6, undated (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W7, undated (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W8, undated (Box 41, Folder 8)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W9, undated (Box 41, Folder 9)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W10, undated (Box 41, Folder 10)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W11, undated (Box 41, Folder 11)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview; M88-105 W12, undated (Box 41, Folder 12)
    - Videotape and film: Interview: Watts/Ammerman, Tape 1; M88-105 W13, 12/14/1988 (Box 41, Folder 13)
    - Videotape and film: Interview: Watts/Ammerman, Tape 2; M88-105 W14, 12/14/1988 (Box 41, Folder 14)
    - Videotape and film: Interview: Watts/Ammerman, Tape 3; M88-105 W15, 12/14/1988 (Box 41, Folder 15)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview, M88-105 W16, 12/21/1988 (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview, M88-105 W17, 12/21/1988 (Box 41, Folder 17)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview, M88-105 W18, 12/21/1988 (Box 41, Folder 18)
      also labeled 88-137-W10 and includes date 01/11/89
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview, M88-105 W19, 01/11/1989 (Box 41, Folder 19)
    - Videotape and film: oral history transcript, interviewed by Thomas M. Perry, 1979 (Box 41, Folder 20)
    - Videotape and film: Dr. Watts interview, M88-105 W20, 12/21/1988 (Box 42, Folder 1)
      labeled B Roll for Dr. Watts
    - Videotape and film: Psychosurgery Oral History, Part I; Interview with James W. Watts, M.D.and Harvey H. Ammerman, M.D. (M88-105), undated (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Videotape and film: Psychosurgery Oral History, Part II; Interview with James W. Watts, M.D.and Harvey H. Ammerman, M.D. (M88-105), undated (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Videotape and film (U-matic tape): Freeman and Watts - Prefrontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Mental Disorders Produced (TRT:15:00) [RESTRICTED], 1941 (Box 42, Folder 4)
      The full video is restricted because a patient is being operated on. A shorter version is available to researchers.
    - Videotape and film (VHS tape): Copy of Freeman and Watts - Prefrontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Mental Disorders, undated (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Videotape and film (DVD): Copy of Freeman and Watts - Prefrontal Lobotomy in the Treatment of Mental Disorders, undated (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Videotape and film (16 mm film): Prefrontal Lobotomy in the treatment of Mental Disorders, 1942 (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Artifacts, 1926-1982; MS0803 SubSubseries 2.9
    - Small brown case containing engraved Wappler Electric Company contains ophthalmoscope and other small tools, undated (Box 43)
    - Plaque Hospital Nacional Neuroligia to Watts for his contributions to neurological science, 1964 (Box 43)
    - Small brown case containing engraved National contains ophthalmoscope and other small tools, undated (Box 43)
    - Putnam ventriculoscope, Electro-Medical Laboratory Inc., undated (Box 43)
    - Framed poem by Ruth Donahue titled "Hands", undated (Box 43)
    - Photographic plate mounted on block of wood - surgery on head, undated (Box 43)
    - Photographic plate mounted on block of wood - surgical tools, undated (Box 43)
    - Radical stab incisor, engraved "Watts-Freeman" (known as 'butterknives'), undated (Box 43)
    - Radical stab incisor, engraved "Dr. J. W. Watts" (known as 'butterknives'), undated (Box 43)
    - Medal given to Dr. J. W. Watts at the International Congress of Neurology, Lisbon, Portugal, 1953 (Box 43)
    - Small box containing seven tools, including hand drill and periosteal elevator (?), labeled Jetter & Scheerer, Germany, undated (Box 43)
    - Electric drill and bits used in surgery [Watts??] labeled "power tool and blades for lobotomy" (Codman & Shurtleff, Inc - Makers - Boston, Mass.), undated (Box 43)
  - James Watts restricted materials
    This subseries contains restricted materials that have been removed from the other subseries in this series. The materials in this series reveal the identies of Dr. Watts' psychiatric patients through the use of names or facially-recognizable photographs.
- Publications - General, 1928-1975; MS0803 Series 3; 1 Linear foot (Box 45, Box 44, Box 46)
  This series contains publications by authors other than Freeman and Watts, and focus primarily on the subject of psychosurgery. Prominent authors include: Sadao Hirose, John Fulton, and Egas Moniz. Not all of the articles are listed at the folder level. The material ranges in date from 1928-75.
  - Publications General A: Ascenzi, Antonio Relationship between Prefrontal Lobes and Thymus (1961); Ackerly, Spafford Instinctive, Emotional and Mental Changes Following Prefrontal Lobe Extirpation (1935); et al, 1935-1961 (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Publications General B: Bowman, Karl Do Our Medical Colleagues Know What to Expect from Psychotherapy? (1954); Brody, Eugene The Response of Schizophrenic Patients to Comic Cartoons (1953); Bailey, Percival The Great Psychiatric Revolution (1956); et al, 1954-1975 (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Publications General C: Cattell, James The Alterations of Ego Functioning After Topectomy (1952); Cooper, Brian Psychiatric Practice in Great Britain and America: A Comparative Study (1967); Constantindes, C.D. Prefrontal Leucotomy (1954); et al, 1949-1967 (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Publications General D: Dynes, John Lobotomy Twenty Years Later (1968 - with correspondence); Diamond, L.S. Results of Lobotomy in Chronic Psychosis (1954); Demille, Richard Intellect After Lobotomy in Schizophrenia (1962); et al, 1954-1968 (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Publications General E: Elithorn, Alick Prefrontal Leucotomy and the Anticipation of Pain (1955); and Autonomic Changes After Unilateral Leucotomy (1954); et al, 1953-1956 (Box 44, Folder 5)
  - Publications General F: Fulton, J.E. The Functions of the Frontal Lobes, A Compaative Study in Monkeys, Chimpanzees and Man (1935); Fernandes, Barahona Egas Moniz and the Pre-frontal Leucotomy (1959); Freyhan, F.A. Prefrontal Lobotomy and Transorbital Leucotomy: A Comparative Study of 175 Patients (1954); Freyhan, F.A. Course and Outcome in Schizophrenia (1955); et al (most in Italian), 1935-1959 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - Publications General G: Greenblatt, Milton Lobotomy in Mental Disease Indications and Results (1954); Gardner, Alexander Transorbital Leucotomy in Noninstituional Cases (1957); et al, 1954-1967 (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - Publications General H: Hirose, Sadao Present Trends in Psychosurgery (1966); Hirose, Sadao Safer Target for Psychosurgery? (1966); Hirose, Sadao Orbitro-Ventromedial Undercutting 1957-63 (1964), 1954-1966 (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - Publications General J: Jackson, C.L. Some Prognostic Factors in 538 Transorbital Lobotomy Cases (1954); James, G.W.B. Theraputic Trauma of the Brain (1951); Jones, Charles H. Transorbital Lobotomy, Preliminary Report of Forty-On Cases (1948); et al, 1936-1955 (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - Publications General K: Kline, Nathan Prognosis in Transorbital Lobotomies Relative to Body Type (1954); Kalinowsky. L.B. Somatic Treatments in Psychiatry (1966); Klotz, Maurice Incidence of Seizures, with EEG Findings, in Prefrontal Lobotomy (1955); et al, 1949-1966 (Box 44, Folder 10)
  - Publications General L: Legault, Oscar Denial as a Complex Process in Post Lobotomy (1954); Levinson, Freda Personality Changes in Relation to Psychiatric Status following Orbital Cortex Undercutting (1965); Lieberson, W.T. Stimulation Studies of the Prefrontal Lobe and Uncus in Man (1951); et al (many in French), 1951-1968 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Publications General: Moniz, Egas Thromboses of the Internal Carotid Artery and Its Branches (with inscription to James Watts 1947); five others in Portuguese (one regarding Freeman), 1936-1956 (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Publications General Mc: McReynolds, Paul The Prediction and Assessment of Psychological Changes Following Prefrontal Lobotomy (1959); McKissock The Present Status of Leucotomy (1960); et al, 1954-1964 (Box 45, Folder 3)